<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>More Right</title>
    <description>My name's Keegan, and this is my blog – it's where I write stuff down after I've given it some thought. Hope you get something useful out of your time here!</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 13:43:16 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 13:43:16 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Graphs from scratch</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;math-education-is-tragic&quot;&gt;Math education is tragic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people despise math. They remember being forced to do arithmetic by hand in elementary school, algebra by hand in middle school, and (sometimes) calculus by hand in high school. They lament the inability to use a calculator when it’s &lt;em&gt;clearly&lt;/em&gt; always going to be possible to do so in ‘real life’. It is an absolute travesty that this process of low-utility algorithmic memorization is what the word ‘mathematics’ has come to mean in the minds of people all around the world. It has deprived billions of grasping the inherent beauty in pondering things that humans can &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; to be true. When done correctly and in the right domain, reductionist reasoning allows one to perceive the numinous in the purest form that the universe can offer it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem with math education, of course, has been noted by people both better at math and better at writing than I. The best explanation of it that I’ve found is &lt;em&gt;A Mathematician’s Lament&lt;/em&gt; by Paul Lockhart (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maa.org/external_archive/devlin/LockhartsLament.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). I recommend you read the whole thing, but this excerpt is particularly salient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Standard School Mathematics Curriculum&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LOWER SCHOOL MATH. The indoctrination begins. Students learn that mathematics is not
something you do, but something that is done to you. Emphasis is placed on sitting still, filling
out worksheets, and following directions. Children are expected to master a complex set of
algorithms for manipulating Hindi symbols, unrelated to any real desire or curiosity on their part,
and regarded only a few centuries ago as too difficult for the average adult. Multiplication tables
are stressed, as are parents, teachers, and the kids themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIDDLE SCHOOL MATH. Students are taught to view mathematics as a set of procedures,
akin to religious rites, which are eternal and set in stone. The holy tablets, or “Math Books,” are
handed out, and the students learn to address the church elders as “they” (as in “What do they
want here? Do they want me to divide?”) Contrived and artificial “word problems” will be
introduced in order to make the mindless drudgery of arithmetic seem enjoyable by comparison.
Students will be tested on a wide array of unnecessary technical terms, such as ‘whole number’
and ‘proper fraction,’ without the slightest rationale for making such distinctions. Excellent
preparation for Algebra I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ALGEBRA I. So as not to waste valuable time thinking about numbers and their patterns, this
course instead focuses on symbols and rules for their manipulation. The smooth narrative thread
that leads from ancient Mesopotamian tablet problems to the high art of the Renaissance
algebraists is discarded in favor of a disturbingly fractured, post-modern retelling with no
characters, plot, or theme. The insistence that all numbers and expressions be put into various
standard forms will provide additional confusion as to the meaning of identity and equality.
Students must also memorize the quadratic formula for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is such breathtaking depth and heartbreaking beauty in this ancient art form. How
ironic that people dismiss mathematics as the antithesis of creativity. They are missing out on an
art form older than any book, more profound than any poem, and more abstract than any abstract.
And it is school that has done this! What a sad endless cycle of innocent teachers inflicting
damage upon innocent students. We could all be having so much more fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you sympathize with everyone that has undergone the experience Lockhart describes. It’s brutalizing. It’s soul-crushing. It’s sickening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I studied math in college and was able to go beyond the layers of nonsense that were piled upon me by the K-12 educational system. I now understand that math is gorgeous, and I understand why people devote their entire lives to studying it. However, most people don’t understand, so I want to give a glimpse of the beauty that I speak of. To do so, we must begin from scratch.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;graphs-from-scratch&quot;&gt;Graphs from scratch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine drawing a dot on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine drawing another dot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now a whole bunch more dots!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so we’ve got a bunch of individual dots, all hanging out in 2-dimensional space. Let’s start connecting them while making sure that every dot is connected to at least one other dot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks pretty cool! Dots and connections between them are what mathematicians call &lt;em&gt;graphs&lt;/em&gt;. The best mathematicians in the world have been studying them, on and off, for about 200 years. This alone should tell you something interesting is happening here –- some of the smartest people in the world that study math full-time, the geekiest of the geeks, devote their entire professional lives to tinkering and studying these simple, cute little things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our imaginations, though. Notice how there are some places in the graph where you if you start at a certain dot and try to get to another dot, there’s no connection? This seems bad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something about our rule from earlier, that ‘every dot needs to be connected to at least one other dot’, isn’t quite good enough. What we need to do is say that ‘starting at any dot in the graph, you need to be able to get to every other dot in the graph by going along the connections’. Let’s try and add some connections so that this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! We can now pick any two dots in the entire graph, and there’s a way to go between them. Mathematicians call graphs where you can do this &lt;em&gt;connected.&lt;/em&gt; Connected graphs are a nice way to think about interesting shapes. For example, these shapes are all connected graphs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the above shapes are pretty, let’s look at two fairly basic connected graphs, the square and the pyramid. The square is nice, we can draw it flatly on paper. The pyramid, though, is a bit trickier. We’re forced to be clever when we squish it onto the paper, and because connections cross each other, it loses the structure that makes it look nice in 3D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img7.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’d be nice if there were some way to represent the dots and connections of the pyramid without having to cleverly squish it down to a 2-dimensional drawing. How might we do this? Try giving it some thought. Think about which features of the graph are important – think about if these two graphs are the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some meaningful way, they are! In 99.9% of cases, mathematicians consider the above two graphs to be &lt;em&gt;identical&lt;/em&gt;. This is kind of weird though – it means that the only important thing about graphs is the dots and the relationships between them! In a way, then, this graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the same thing as saying ‘There are 3 dots. Dot 1 and dot 2 are connected, dot 2 and dot 3 are connected, and dot 3 and dot 1 are connected.’ Let’s invent some way of expressing that with less words. If two dots are connected, let’s put them in some parentheses and separate them by a comma, like this: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(dot_{1},dot_{2})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can do better. Instead of calling them dot 1 and dot 2, let’s just use their numbers, like this: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1,2)&lt;/script&gt;. The order of the numbers doesn’t matter though, so we could flip-flop any of them inside of their parentheses if we wanted to. In a way, these numbers and parentheses really &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; the dots and edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, if we want to talk about a bunch of the dots and edges, we just list a bunch of those numbers and parentheses, like this: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1,2), (2,3), (3,1)&lt;/script&gt;. It looks weird to not enclose those pairs of parentheses and numbers with something though, and it would be confusing to just use more parentheses, so let’s use curly braces, like this: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\{(1,2), (2,3), (3,1)\}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematicians have fancy names for all of the ideas that we just came up with, but fancy names make it hard to focus on the part of math that matters, so I’m not mentioning them here. If you want to read more, check out this footnote.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to that pyramid from earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img12.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish our goal of representing the dots and connections of the pyramid without having to cleverly squish the 3-dimensional shape down to 2, all we have to do is label the dots and translate their connections into numbers and parentheses. Easy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pyramid is actually just this list of pairs of numbers in parentheses: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\{(1,2),(2,3),(3,1),(1,4),(2,4),(3,4)\}&lt;/script&gt;. There’s a lot of repeated stuff in that list of parentheses and numbers though, so maybe there’s a better way to keep track of all the information. Let’s try doing that with a square of numbers, where if there’s a connection between dot a and dot b, we put a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; in the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a&lt;/script&gt;th column and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt;th row of the square. That’s a lot to think about at once, so let’s go one pair of numbers in the list at a time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have 4 dots, so we need 4 columns and 4 rows in our square of numbers. Because of this, notice how we’ll always end up using &lt;em&gt;squares&lt;/em&gt; instead of ugly rectangles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix}0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably noticed that this is just a matrix. Matrices are, as it turns out, useful ways of encoding information about graphs. The word ‘matrix’ is burned into most peoples’ minds as quasi-traumatic though, and matrices are fundamentally just squares and rectangles of numbers, so I’ll keep calling them that. Now, the first pair is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1,2)&lt;/script&gt;, so let’s put a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; in the spot at the 1st column and 2nd row:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix}0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the order of the numbers in the pair doesn’t matter, so we also have to remember the pair &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(2,1)&lt;/script&gt; and put a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; in the spot at the 2nd column and 1st row:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix}0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how there’s a symmetry to the square! Because order doesn’t matter for the numbers in the pair, whichever pair you choose will always have a &lt;em&gt;twin&lt;/em&gt; pair where the numbers are flipped. In our number-square, the twins show up on the opposite side of the diagonal that runs from the top left to the bottom right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do one more example of putting a pair and its twin into the square. The next pair in the original list is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(2,3)&lt;/script&gt;, and its twin is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(3,2)&lt;/script&gt;, so we put &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt;s in the 2nd column and 3rd row, and the 3rd column and 2nd row:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix}0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll fill out the rest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix}0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woah! I hope you think this is cool! This beautiful looking square of numbers just popped out of nowhere! Let’s think about it though – why would we have a square where everything is filled in except the diagonal? I encourage you to stop and try to reason through it. If you’re not feeling up to it though, that’s cool too – just look below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the spaces in the main diagonal represent connections between a dot and itself, but we don’t have any of those in the pyramid. The math-y word for ‘a connection between a dot and itself’ is a &lt;em&gt;loop.&lt;/em&gt; Loops look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img11.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if a graph has no loops, then its corresponding square of numbers will have 0s in the main diagonal. But what about all the 1s? Why is &lt;em&gt;every other possible spot&lt;/em&gt; in the graph’s number-square filled with a 1? Well, it’s because &lt;em&gt;every dot in the graph is connected directly to every other dot.&lt;/em&gt; Look at the pyramid again, and think about this for a second:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graphs-from-scratch/img10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whichever dot I pick in the pyramid, I can get to any other dot by only going across one connection! Mathematicians call this kind of graph &lt;em&gt;dense.&lt;/em&gt; We just figured out something really interesting – if we take a random, perhaps extremely complicated graph, and go through this simple operation of translating it into pairs of numbers and then a square of numbers, we can &lt;em&gt;instantly&lt;/em&gt; see whether or not it’s dense. All we have to do is check if there are any zeroes that &lt;em&gt;aren’t&lt;/em&gt; on the diagonal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with nothing but our intuition and pictures, then made up a language for thinking about those pictures, then made up another language to think about our first language, and out popped a beautiful relationship! We can now translate &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; graph into a number-square, and it magically becomes incredibly easy to know whether or not that graph is dense. We took a normally very complicated, difficult-to-test property, and made it easy enough for a pre-schooler to check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This&lt;/em&gt; is what math is. Math is the act of starting somewhere interesting and just messing around, playing, until cool things start popping out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s enthralling, it’s visceral, and it’s extremely fun. Reasoning from scratch is one of the purest joys that our world has to offer, and I hope you see at least some of the beauty and appeal of doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m deeply sorry if it wasn’t shown to you any earlier in your life, but now is your opportunity to go out and explore!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in stuff like this, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xdIjYBtnvZU&quot;&gt;3blue1brown&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube. He makes beautiful videos that take you on this same type of mental adventure. The numinous awaits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Putting two numbers inside of parentheses is called a &lt;em&gt;pair.&lt;/em&gt; When it doesn’t matter in which order we put the numbers inside of the parentheses, it’s called an &lt;em&gt;unordered pair,&lt;/em&gt; and we’d write that for whatever dots you want, call them dot a and dot b, we have that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(a,b)=(b,a)&lt;/script&gt;. When it does matter in which order we put the numbers, it’s called an &lt;em&gt;ordered pair,&lt;/em&gt; and we’d write that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(a,b) \ne (b,a)&lt;/script&gt;. If the order of the dots in the parentheses doesn’t matter for the entire graph, we call the graph &lt;em&gt;undirected.&lt;/em&gt; If the order of the dots does matter, we call the graph &lt;em&gt;directed.&lt;/em&gt; The connections between dots in directed graphs are usually drawn with arrows instead of lines, because you can think of there being a correct way of going from one dot to another. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/graphs-from-scratch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/graphs-from-scratch</guid>
        
        <category>math</category>
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The illusory stupidity of politicians</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;American media has a long history of portraying politicians, and people of power more generally, as stupid and naive. Saturday Night Live’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JUWSLlz0Fdo&amp;amp;list=PLIMQGnRxY3JH4jtVG5zjmW0Eqqt_jzWSF&quot;&gt;political skits&lt;/a&gt; are wonderful examples of this. SNL has a distinctly liberal lean, and so tends to focus on GOP figures, but there are many examples of analogous media portrayals from the conservative side of the Overton window, too. Articles and TV segments abound from all across the political spectrum that propound the blatant idiocy and plebeian nature of the other side’s figureheads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the media portrayals, are politicians actually stupid and naive? I think the answer is a resounding &lt;em&gt;hell no&lt;/em&gt;. Take someone like Steve Bannon, who has been pilloried by the media (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2018/01/04/steve-bannon-michael-wolff-book-donald-trump-216243&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themarysue.com/steve-bannon-stupid-trump-documentary/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedailybeast.com/steve-bannon-has-become-the-one-thing-we-never-thought-hed-be-boring&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). It seems to me that the general characterization of Steve Bannon is as a naive, corrupt, sometimes idiotic, and boring guy. If you’re politically liberal and reading this, I’d guess that you agree (if you don’t, send me an email or a DM!). Now, try to gently put that conception aside for a moment and watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qH5QzuzD01A&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; of him discussing China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first saw it, I was blown away at how articulate he was and how parsimonious some of his explanations were. Surely there was a mistake. This was &lt;em&gt;Steve Bannon&lt;/em&gt;, a known dumbass, a ‘lying, fascist prick!’ That fool couldn’t possibly be referencing 老百姓 and Chinese political philosophy! He just, you know, spends all day reading the shit that Breitbart writers spew… he, he…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I implore you to try this exercise with any politician you think is stupid or naive (with the exception of Trump – Trump seems to either be (1) a counterexample to this pattern, or (2) secretly intelligent). Try and find a longer interview or piece of writing from the politician that was created during a period when they weren’t in the heyday of their political career. I suspect that you’ll be surprised by their cogency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question then becomes &lt;em&gt;why?&lt;/em&gt; Why are we deluded by the media about the intelligence and ability of our politicians?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation is that it’s just another example of partisan conflict. The powers that be on either side of the political spectrum want their political opposition to seem stupid, naive, weak, etc. so that voters are less inclined to vote for said opposition. While perhaps correct, this is uninteresting. It’s the same story we’ve heard for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more interesting question to ask is not just ‘why are we deluded by the media’, but rather &lt;em&gt;why do people eat it up?&lt;/em&gt; The media can propagate whatever messaging it wants, but at some fundamental level, the populace has to swallow what it’s being fed. Various psychological tricks are routinely used to make the act of swallowing easier on us poor bastards, but there must be some degree of deep acceptance of the information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the illusory stupidity of politicians, I’d chalk it up to an innate desire to feel as though one is smarter than one actually is. It’s tempting to believe that you could be doing what the politicians are doing. It’s tempting to tell yourself that if circumstances had been a bit different, if you had really given it a good college try, you could &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; have gotten elected. In the safety of your own head, it’s all too easy to ‘know’ that you’re an expert on the issues that face the nation and the difficulties of becoming an elected official.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dunning-Kruger effect rears its ugly head here – most Americans simply aren’t conscientious enough to realize that the world of foreign affairs and public policy is extremely difficult to think about and act competently inside of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most things are like this! &lt;em&gt;Perhaps the world is a bit more complex than how the media portrays it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/the-illusory-stupidity-of-politicians</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/the-illusory-stupidity-of-politicians</guid>
        
        <category>politics</category>
        
        <category>media</category>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Literature as evidence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a long history of social-scientists using literature as foundational evidence for their ideas and theories. If you want proof of such a claim, go take a look at the now archaic &lt;em&gt;Totem and Taboo&lt;/em&gt; or even the OG &lt;em&gt;Communist Manifesto&lt;/em&gt;. For a more modern version, just crack open &lt;em&gt;Things Hidden since the Foundation of the World&lt;/em&gt;. You’ll be inundated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, this seems laughable. Literature? As scientific evidence? Aren’t most great works of literature &lt;em&gt;fictional?&lt;/em&gt; How can something fictional possibly be used rigorously?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, it cannot! Obviously, one should not use fictional literature as &lt;em&gt;rigorous, scientific&lt;/em&gt; evidence in the sense of ‘providing explicit information about an event or occurrence.’ If I claim that Alice killed Bob (the poor bastard), and then justify my claim by citing a classic Dostoevsky novel where Alice kills Bob (in this hypothetical world, such a novel exists), you’d rightly inform me of my idiocy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As scholars of the humanities and social sciences love to point out, rigorous science isn’t everything. Speaking from experience, this is a hard pill to swallow. Despite the fact that extracting precise scientific value from literature is nearly impossible, literature does have an interesting characteristic that allows for the embedding and subsequent extraction of useful information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characteristic of which I speak stems from the fact that literature is a subset of books, and books are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect&quot;&gt;Lindy&lt;/a&gt;. This means that any literature in the zeitgeist of the current day has survived the cumulative literary scrutiny of all human beings who lived between the publishing of such literature and now. This is an extremely difficult thing to do, which is why we see such a tiny number of pieces of older literature that have maintained their high graces in the cultural tastes of every era since they were published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a useful trait! We can roughly deduce that old literature that has been in the zeitgeist for a long time encodes something deep about the preferences of human beings. I suspect this is the utility that people like Freud, Marx, and Girard see in it. Analyzing literature is then akin to analyzing a highly-agreed-upon version of human values and preferences, something that is extremely valuable if you’re studying human values and preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time that you encounter a claim that makes use of literature for evidence, do your best to evaluate it while keeping the above characteristic in mind. Social science often seems like useless and obscurantist gobbledegook, but some of the people that operate in this space know what they’re doing, and their ideas are good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sláinte!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/literature-as-evidence</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/literature-as-evidence</guid>
        
        <category>literature</category>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A new era of more right</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-explanation&quot;&gt;an explanation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is the day that I begin surfacing words from my personal reflection-journal/digital-thought-notebook thing. I have a (sort of) daily cadence of writing in it, because doing so helps me keep my head on straight. If I don’t work through the ambient thoughts in my brain in a systematic way like this, the thoughts either implode into nothingness or explode into existential and epistemic anxiety. Both of those outcomes are bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, I tweeted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/keegan_mcnamara/status/1188337574299013120&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; the other day, so I figured that instead of perpetuating the problems I pointed out, I’d start trying to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of me hates disturbing the former serenity and distilled nature of this website with something as filthy and unkempt as mere &lt;em&gt;thoughts&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;reflections&lt;/em&gt; (the bile bubbles to the back of my throat as I type), but I’ve decided that if there’s any net positive effect on humanity as a result of my making such things public, then I ought to do it. As anyone who has taken an Analysis course knows, net positivity is not difficult to do ( &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\forall \epsilon &gt; 0,\exists...&lt;/script&gt;), so I think I indeed ought to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-changes&quot;&gt;some changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d still like there to be features that allow for some semblance of filterability on my writings, so I’ve added a &lt;a href=&quot;https://keeganm.org/categories&quot;&gt;categories&lt;/a&gt; page and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://keeganm.org/tags&quot;&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt; page. Implementing categories and tags from scratch in Jekyll was a bit of a pain in the ass, but I think it’ll be worth it in the longer term. I also have a fair number of thoughts about math and physics-related things, so I added MathJax support (do you even &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\LaTeX&lt;/script&gt;, bro?) for when I desperately need to reminisce on the days I spent breathing in toxic amounts of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PhNUjg9X4g8&quot;&gt;Hagoromo&lt;/a&gt; dust. Again, Jekyll is kind of a pain in the ass to do stuff like this with, but as my good friend Brennie would say, the ‘worth is high’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be categorizing these more spontaneous thoughts and writings as ‘posts’, as opposed to the far more time-consuming to produce ‘essays’ and ‘videos’. Perhaps someday I’ll gather the courage to put my poetry and prose on here. We’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also changed the look and feel of the site. More specifically…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I changed the paragraph font to what I consider the most beautiful of all serifs, Libre Baskerville. I previously used Helvetica, which is nice for headings, but miserable to read for long periods of time. Such is the life of a sans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I removed all of the colors from the site, with the notable exception of salmon (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff5858;&quot;&gt;#ff5858&lt;/span&gt;). I use the same salmon color on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/keegan_mcnamara&quot;&gt;twitter profile&lt;/a&gt;, and I enjoy having a cohesive brand identity in this one, very limited way. I’m also a proponent of design minimalism, which leads me to…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I thinned out all of the lines used for bounding boxes. This allows the elements on the screen to breathe, and it also focuses attention on the ones that matter. The bounding boxes themselves are actually totally unnecessary, but I like how they demarcate territory and group related elements together. They’re also somewhat of an homage to Engelbart and Kay’s invention of the notion of ‘windows’ for computer graphical user interfaces (read more &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_graphical_user_interface&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Rectangles are cool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s everything pertinent that I can think of for the moment. Sláinte!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/a-new-era-of-more-right</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/a-new-era-of-more-right</guid>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Essay in Palladium Magazine</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote a piece for Palladium about the video game industry, the increasingly exploitative tools it uses to gain/retain users, and why we need change. Read it &lt;a href=&quot;https://palladiummag.com/2019/09/12/the-siren-call-of-video-games-amid-decaying-social-fabric/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/palladium-piece</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/palladium-piece</guid>
        
        <category>gaming</category>
        
        <category>governance</category>
        
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sport and Invisible Propaganda</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You know the feeling. You’re at the stadium, the anthem is being sung while a wounded veteran is paraded around next to the professional players. Tears well in your eyes, and it’s as though a balloon filled with liquid pride is gradually expanding in your upper abdomen. It’s incredibly unique – I, frankly, can’t think of more than a handful of instances wherein such a deep appreciation and sense of pride can be brought about in myself as if due to the flip of a switch. But why? Why does every American who’s ever seen a professional sports event know this feeling so vividly and experience it so intensely?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noam Chomsky would probably turn to his propaganda model of media for an explanation. In its essence, Chomsky would say, the media’s primary purpose is as a tool to indoctrinate and suppress the masses. Prima facie, perhaps that claim sounds like just another academic spewing some “goddamned anti-American garbage.” But consider for a moment the perspective of a Martian peering down on America from outer space. This Martian would see a truly remarkable concentration of power and wealth within the government and the largest corporations. It seems to follow immediately that because humans are greedy creatures, those entities that control the vast majority of power and wealth in the US would want to continue to control that power and wealth. So then, as the astute Martian would point out, it makes perfect sense that those institutions would utilize a significant amount of the vast resources at their disposal to maintain their respective stakes. Well, as it were, some of the largest companies in the US are media companies. In addition to huge sums of capital, they control massive information distribution networks (e.g. TV, radio, social media, etc…), and the Martian would see that those networks and that capital were being appropriated to mold the public’s conception of the world away from the reality of corporate and governmental fascism and instead inculcate them with docility in order to maintain the status quo of power and wealth. What’s frightening about Chomsky’s model is that it’s coldly rational, unbiased politically, and posits that the existence of the propagandistic media is merely an emergent property of the concentrations of wealth that arise in capitalistic societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this lens, let’s take a deeper look at the culture of sports in modern society. Consider a relatively simple question that actually cuts quite deeply into the issue – why are athletes in the NFL paid so much money? Well, perhaps the prima facie answer is that they’re just extremely well qualified on a physical basis, and therefore deserving of special pay. Consider though that professional marathon runners, who are extremely well qualified on a physical basis (perhaps even moreso than NFL players), make vastly less money than NFL players. For example, Tamirat Tola, a 2016 Olympic Bronze medalist from Ethiopia, made a paltry $93,750 in 2018, while Jimmy Garropolo, the QB for the San Francisco 49ers, made $43,100,000. Physical qualification can’t be the answer. However, things become clear when you look at how much sponsorship money is being spent on each sport, and from who that money is coming. The NFL’s sponsorship revenue totaled $1.32 Billion in the 2017-2018 season, while the Professional Road Running Organization’s (PRRO) total prize money available for the 2018 season was a mere $330,000. The NFL’s sponsors are companies like Anheuser-Busch, Castrol, PepsiCo, and Frito-Lay, whereas the PRRO’s sponsors are companies like Publix (a grocery-store chain) and a small credit union in Washington DC. The NFL players are making more money because there’s a helluva lot more institutional money being poured into their market. The natural question to ask then is this: why aren’t companies like Anheuser-Busch and PepsiCo sponsoring the PRRO circuit? Well, it’s because the American public isn’t watching televised marathons – they’re watching their favorite NFL, MLB, NHL, and NBA teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People put a pretty astonishingly large amount of time and mental resources into sports. If you ask your next-door neighbor how your local NFL team is doing, you’re likely to get an extremely articulate and complex response that takes into account the abilities of individual players, the coaching staff’s play calling decisions, the player trading market, etc… They’re probably going to cite specific statistics and be able to discuss intricacies that required hours of observation, research, and thought. And it makes sense – in our society, there are things that people can use their intelligence on, take politics for example, but most can’t really get involved in those things in any meaningful way. So instead, they spend their intelligence on other things that are cognitively intensive, yet also accessible – things like spectator sports. Sports intensely occupy the minds of a vast majority of the population and diffuse a huge amount of latent time and intellectual capacity, which is precisely what the corporate and governmental entities that control the majority of power and wealth would want. So it’s quite natural that companies like Anheuser-Busch and PepsiCo are sponsoring the big spectator sports associations – those associations are doing a wonderful thing in the eyes of such companies. They’re efficiently squandering the time and cognitive effort of the broader populace that could otherwise be used to gain a deeper understanding of reality and potentially organize to bring about change in the upper echelons of power. Furthermore, it makes total sense that the armed forces show up, parade around veterans, and hold subtly nationalist ceremonies – they’re the grandaddy of the entities that have a vested interest in supporting such a quiescence of the broader populace. In an attempt to not inflame passions, I’ll leave that discussion to Chomsky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s return to our initial situation. You’re watching your favorite team play, and you rise for the national anthem. Your heart swells with pride as the talented singer belts the anthem alongside a wounded veteran. With our newfound understanding, though, the sentiment of that situation changes. Spectator sports enforce jingoism, promote consumerism, and indoctrinate an impressionable society to maintain the status quo of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think before you buy that ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/sport-and-invisible-propaganda</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/sport-and-invisible-propaganda</guid>
        
        <category>social-observation</category>
        
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Only Reason College Prestige Matters</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Harvard. Stanford. MIT. Princeton. Yale. Northwestern. Johns Hopkins. UChicago. Berkeley. Columbia. Dartmouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all names that bring about strong emotions in most people. For some, those emotions are jealousy, anger, and disdain. For most others, they’re prestige, respect, and mystique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why do such institutions hold such high places in our hearts and minds? Why do we value graduates of that set of prestigious schools so much more than all of the others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s solely because it’s hard to get in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that when I’m looking at someone’s LinkedIn profile or resume, the biggest “wow!” factor is a degree from a prestigious institution. And the reason I’ve come up with to explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is not at all because of the things that they’ve learned while walking the hallowed halls of such places — anecdotally, the content and quality of an education varies very little within US colleges. Calc 3 at Stanford is pretty damn similar to Calc 3 at The University of Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, the degree indicates to me that the person was given a stamp of approval by one of the most difficult, rigorous filtering processes that the world has to offer — the admissions committee. Any Stanford freshman in this year’s class of 2022 was among only 4.36% of students to be accepted. Read that one more time. &lt;strong&gt;Four point three six percent.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sum total of a student’s entire life, both academic and otherwise, was evaluated by a brutally harsh committee of Stanford gatekeepers, and that student was let in. Those gatekeepers pored over every detail on that person’s admission profile and thought that they stood out among &lt;strong&gt;47,451&lt;/strong&gt; applicants. That’s remarkable, and indicates an immense amount of skill, dedication, and tenacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, it means they were a badass early on in their lives. Whether it was through parental pressures, natural talent, or whatever else, they pursued and achieved incredible things while they were less than ~18 years old. It’s &lt;em&gt;guaranteed&lt;/em&gt; that they did. And that’s why it’s valuable when I see it on a resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing this, I’m essentially just bootstrapping the sum total expertise and experience of those admissions committees and leveraging it to make a more informed opinion of a person. The probability that someone who has demonstrated badassery to the degree needed to get into an elite school will go on to continue demonstrating badassery thereafter (in any given area of their life) is &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; higher than the probability that someone who graduated from community college after dropping out of high school will do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this explanation to be deeply satisfying— it explains why I hold MIT drop-outs in the same raw intellectual talent regard as I hold people who spent the full 4 years at MIT. It explains why I hold Dartmouth graduates from the 70’s in far lower raw talent regard than the Dartmouth freshmen of today. It explains why I hold Harvard undergrads who go on to PhD programs at CU Boulder in higher talent regard than CU Boulder undergrads who go on to PhD programs at Harvard. And most of all, it explains why people who list Stanford as their education on LinkedIn after completing an online course on Udacity or Coursera are not impressive to me &lt;em&gt;whatsoever&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my evaluation, it’s all about leveraging the effort, research, and expertise of the admissions councils in order to establish a base confidence in the likelihood of a given person to be a badass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This outlook is the most effective in the case where I’m considering people who are either currently enrolled in college or are recent graduates/drop outs. From there on out, where they went doesn’t matter as much as what they ended up doing for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is best shown with an example. If Jill went to Yale but then worked for Deloitte for 10 years and did nothing of interest except earn one promotion, Jill is not a badass (in my book). If Joe went to Washington State but then worked for Google as a Software Engineer for 2 years and started 3 companies, one of which failed, one of which was sold for 200mm, and one of which was acquihired by Microsoft, I no longer care that he went to Washington State — he’s sufficiently demonstrated his badassery to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while it’s totally feasible for edge cases to occur on both sides of the spectrum, telling ourselves romantic stories about them leads to false general perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take one of my good friends from high school who was incredibly intelligent and an undeniable badass, but was denied admission at the Ivies he applied to. He ended up going to CU Boulder. Just because of this edge case, we shouldn’t tell ourselves a false narrative that CU Boulder graduates are as competent on average as MIT graduates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other end, take a guy I met this past summer who was undoubtedly dumb. He had extremely poor technical abilities, didn’t learn quickly, and couldn’t communicate his thoughts in an effective way. He’s a Junior at Princeton. Just because of this edge case, we shouldn’t tell ourselves a false narrative that Princeton graduates are as competent on average as UMass Amherst graduates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a tough pill to swallow as a college student at a less prestigious school. It means that you’ll likely have a more difficult time getting started in your professional career. Remember that all hope is not lost, however. If you can prove yourself by doing incredible things and persevering through the ‘prestige gap’, you can surpass anyone that may have come out of an Ivy league school or other top ranked institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if you’re a college student at a prestigious school, you have a leg up out of the gates. But if you squander your career pursuing unimpressive, safe, or boring opportunities, you’ll lose your lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, it’s most important &lt;em&gt;by far&lt;/em&gt; to take risks and do cool things. The majority of your life is spent &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; in college, so make it count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/the-only-reason-college-prestige-matters</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/the-only-reason-college-prestige-matters</guid>
        
        <category>college</category>
        
        <category>social-observation</category>
        
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savor the Cereal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I wasn’t an awesome human being. I didn’t try very hard in any of my classes, I played too many video games, I didn’t read enough, I ate like shit, and I exercised only when I felt so disgusted with myself that it felt like a fucking moral imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to unearth my true potential, but I also knew that there wasn’t an ice cube’s chance in hell of that potential being actualized unless I changed my life in a really fundamental way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That way came through reading. I forced myself to read 14 books in 2 weeks while working full-time at Amazon, and I learned some cool shit from some great writers like Atul Gawande, Nick Bostrom, and Ray Dalio. The books I read collectively sparked in me a deep-seated desire to re-evaluate my life and create a framework for self improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That framework manifested itself in an increased drive to do certain thing and undergo periods of harsh self-reflection that then informed plans to create a rigorous routine of hard work and discipline. It also manifested itself in an increased need to consume ideas and thoughts in the form of reading books, Medium articles, blog posts, and Quora answers, watching terrific thought-pieces on YouTube, great documentaries on Netflix, and awesome short-films on Vimeo, and listening to podcasts from some of the great thinkers of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It. Was. Fucking. Incessant. I spent damn near every waking minute consuming thoughts and ideas. Podcasts for breakfast, Podcasts while I was driving (one earbud out for safety!), YouTube videos during my lunch break, Medium articles as a mental break from coding, and documentaries late at night when I couldn’t focus anymore. I devoured media &lt;em&gt;voraciously.&lt;/em&gt; And this was the “good” media, too. The kind that everyone and their mother tells you to consume instead of the shitty news updates you see on Snapchat, Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram. I used said apps for a combined 10 minutes a day, just to make sure I wasn’t missing out on the US being bombed or some similarly important, historic event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I was doing great — being aware and motivated towards self improvement wasn’t the norm for people my age. I felt like I was succeeding in a culture where it was all too common to spend day after day drinking from the endless dopamine-fountain that is social media. But for some reason, at the end of every day, I felt just as empty as when I woke up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This went on for some time, before I finally realized that I wasn’t &lt;em&gt;being.&lt;/em&gt; I was constantly in the &lt;strong&gt;on&lt;/strong&gt; position — thinking, reading, wondering, journaling, making note of the things that I was learning, engaging with people, etc…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not once did I stop. Not once did I &lt;em&gt;smell the goddamn roses&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next day, instead of listening to the new Sam Harris podcast while I scarfed down some cereal in an effort to get to the gym on schedule for my daily routine, I put my phone away and &lt;em&gt;just ate the fucking cereal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of pondering the ethics of honor culture while listening to the eloquent neuroscience PhD talk on 1.5x speed, I slowed down and tasted every single bite of that bowl of Honey Bunches of Oats that went into my mouth. Every delectable calorie that lay in the bowl below me was appreciated as it crossed my palate and subsequently slid down my gullet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever realized that Honey Bunches of Oats is mostly just Corn Flakes and Frosted Flakes mixed together in an orgy of carbs? I sure as shit know that I hadn’t prior to that fateful morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was &lt;em&gt;magical&lt;/em&gt; to slow down, be present in the moment, and be aware of how amazing the most mundane stuff in our lives is. I mean, it was &lt;em&gt;cereal&lt;/em&gt; for chrissakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since then, I’ve made sure that I take the time every day to stop being so constantly &lt;strong&gt;on&lt;/strong&gt; and slow down to realize the wonderment that can be seen in every nook and cranny of ordinary being. &lt;strong&gt;That&lt;/strong&gt; is what has made me a better person and realize my potential in a fuller manner. No amount of podcasts, books, or thought-pieces can help you see the miraculous nature of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consuming is not being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Savor the cereal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/savor-the-cereal</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/savor-the-cereal</guid>
        
        <category>self-improvement</category>
        
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>there are no extraterrestrial intelligent beings</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/L3CmtYWO5b4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/no-extraterrestrial-intelligent-beings</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/no-extraterrestrial-intelligent-beings</guid>
        
        <category>artificial-intelligence</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        
        <category>video</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>traveling as an antidote</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lFePBA--Xe8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/traveling-as-an-antidote</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/traveling-as-an-antidote</guid>
        
        <category>self-improvement</category>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        
        <category>video</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
